SAQIB ARFEEN

Berlin, Germany

saqib.arfeen@gmail.com | github.com/saqibarfeen | linkedIn.com/in/mohamedsaqib

SUMMARY

Software engineer • Backend engineer • Data engineer

Software engineer with 7 years of specialised experience in SaaS, No-code, ERP, Cloud, and Big Data.

Recognised for deep technical expertise and tackling research-intensive challenges, often pioneering groundbreaking methodologies.

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: JavaScript, TypeScript, C++, Java, Python, Go
- Programming Frameworks: Spring, Express, React, Netsuite SuiteCloud Platform, Nvidia CUDA
- Databases: Postgres, MySQL, MongoDB, ElasticSearch, Graphite, InfluxDB, Hadoop, Spark, Ninox
- Cloud & Distributed Systems: OpenStack, AWS Lambda EC2 EKS SQS SES, Hadoop MapReduce, Kafka, RabbitMQ, Redis
- SRE/DevOps: Kubernetes, Prometheus, CI/CD with Circle CI and Github Actions, Ansible, Puppet, Nagios, Icinga
- Data Visualisation: Grafana, Kibana

EXPERIENCE

Ninox Software GmbH (ninox.com), Berlin

Nov 2022 – Present

Senior Software Engineer

- Contributed to engineering high-impact features that elevated product competitiveness and quality, correlating with a growth of 25% in ARR.
- Conceptualised and prototyped software architectures, effectively bridging technical possibilities with product vision through close collaboration with product owners.

Seed Labs, Karachi

Oct 2021 – Sep 2022

A startup company building a decentralised exchange (DEX) for crypto derivatives.

Senior Software Engineer

- Designed and implemented a robust persistence and fault-tolerance mechanism using Kafka, elevating system resilience and data integrity.
- Achieved a 10x improvement in build times by meticulously instrumenting and optimising critical backend components, including the order-matching engine and blockchain settlement layer
- Executed a strategic migration to Kubernetes, resulting in an 80% reduction in fixed infrastructure costs, enhancing scalability and operational efficiency.

Folio3 Software Inc, Karachi

Nov 2019 - Sep 2021

Senior Software Engineer

- As a Senior Engineer on the Netsuite ERP team, spearheaded the development of business process customisations and integrations, delivering high-quality projects that fostered long-term partnerships with multiple Fortune 500 companies.
- Initiated and curated an in-house knowledge base focused on ERP design patterns and business workflows, resulting in a 50% reduction in development costs for routine projects.

Ivolve Technologies, Karachi

Jun 2019 - Nov 2019

Senior Software Engineer

- Recruited, trained and helped build the team to transition the product development from an outsourced contractor to in-house, increasing agility and reducing time to market.
- Hybrid-cloud Middleware: Integrated OpenStack with other cloud services.
- Monitoring system: Developed a Single Pane of Glass monitoring solution for OpenStack's cloud using tools including Ceilometer, Gnocchi, ElasticSearch, Graphite and Grafana.

Cloud 9 Networks, Karachi

July 2016 - May 2019

Software Engineer

- Onboarded when the founders started to build a big-data software solution for a large "customer loyalty card payment system" within the MENA region. Later developed two more products from zero to production.
- Played a key role in the research, design and implementation of various SaaS products including B2B
 Business Intelligence, OpenStack cloud monitoring and network infrastructure monitoring.
- Built the products in cycles of weeks instead of months e.g bit.ly/siem-saqib
- Trained new developers, and helped them become effective engineers at the company.
- Pivoted and delivered a new product for Actionable Intelligence in IT that won the contract from a top telecom provider of Pakistan.

EDUCATION

BS, Computer Science CGPA: 3.03/4.0

FAST National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences, Karachi Registration No. 12K-2322

CERTIFICATIONS

- Coursera: The Data Scientist's Toolbox (CZ4FS4J6T972)
- Coursera: AI for Everyone (F926BXSQE638)
- Coursera: Tensorflow on Google Cloud (KJ3QWPW3FJUT)
- Coursera: IBM Cloud Private: Deploying Microservices with Kubernetes (LD83GGMJ84L5)
- Coursera: Neural Networks and Deep Learning (UMRA4C82PK8V)